<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Infant-baptism vindicated from the exceptions of Mr. Thomas Grantham by Sam. Petto ...</title>
            <author>Petto, Samuel, 1624?-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35388</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15272431</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15272431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1191:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Infant-baptism vindicated from the exceptions of Mr. Thomas Grantham by Sam. Petto ...</title>
                  <author>Petto, Samuel, 1624?-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Ed. Giles ... and T. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692. --  Presumption no proof.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103339:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:103339:1"/> Infant-Baptiſm VINDICATED FROM THE EXCEPTIONS OF
M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Thomas Grantham.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM. PETTO,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in
<hi>SUDBURY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts 2. 39.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Promiſe is unto you, and to your
Children.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Ed. Giles,</hi>
Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>T. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the
<hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103339:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103339:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere is ſuch Scripture-Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for Infant-Baptiſm, that
intelligent, unprejudiced Men may find what Mr.</hi> Grantham <hi>ſaith
againſt my Defence of it, a Reply, and no Anſwer; Preſumption, and no
Proof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Practice of that Perſon which withdrew from our
Communion, was ſuch as (if admitted) is deſtructive to all Goſpel of
Church-Order, and ſo is no ſlight Occaſion to write upon: But I had other
weighty Matters enſuing, which neceſſitated my Writing; and Mr.</hi>
Grantham <hi>(not being medled with) can ſhew none ſuch for his
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:103339:3"/> 
               <hi>As to what he ſaith to me, I ſhall very
briefly anſwer, being ſtill of the ſame Mind that I was of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let all
be meaſured by the Rule of the Word: And that thou mayeſt have
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding therein, ſhall be the Prayer of him, who is</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine to ſerve thee In the Goſpel, Sam.
Petto.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 12. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103339:3"/>
            <head>Infant-Baptiſm VINDICATED.</head>
            <p>INfants were diverſified by the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,
Gen.</hi> 17. and ſo ſtill may be by the Will of Chriſt, all not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Seed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Argument, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. was <hi>Ad Hominem,</hi> as appears
there, and by my Poſtſcript; and ſaith only, <hi>[That Infant-Baptiſm
is not expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, therefore either it is lawful, or elſe
Scripture-Conſequences must be admitted,]</hi> which is undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. It was
occaſioned by my being told in a Conference, that there ſhould be expreſs
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in ſuch a Caſe; therefore it was not my Miſtake. Neither is my
Argument anſwered by ſaying, as he doth, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>[There is no
expreſs Scripture for Infant-Baptiſm, therefore Infant-Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm may be
omitted.]</hi> This is falſe; for there is no expreſs Scripture for Women's
Receiving the Lord's Supper, and divers other things, yet they may not be
omitted, becauſe by Scripture-Conſequences, rightly deduced, they are
requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And hence I can ſubſcribe to every Word which he mentions of
that Author of our own, <hi>p.</hi> 2. and to <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Rule; I am
of the ſame Mind; there is nothing therein againſt my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and I can
eaſily withſtand any Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is not expreſly forbidden in
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103339:4"/> for <hi>I think things may be commanded or
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by good Scripture-Conſequence:</hi> And it was and is my Judgment,
<hi>that all in the Worſhip of God muſt be commanded there, either
expreſly, or by neceſſary Conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> at his firſt beginning with me, and
frequently after, by a multitude of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Words, would make his
incautelous Reader believe, that I bring Scriptures for one purpoſe, which
are brought for another. As, <hi>p.</hi> 4. I bring <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 3. and 9.
1. to prove that to be a Church-Member is, in Scripture, to be a Diſciple;
whereas he would have it believed, that I thereby would immediately prove
Infants Diſciples, <hi>p.</hi> 4. So the Scriptures by which I prove,
<hi>p.</hi> 5. that the Name <hi>[Holy]</hi> is given to Father, Son and
Spirit, as, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 15. Lev.</hi> 19. 2. and 20. 7. <hi>Heb. 7. 26,
&amp;c.</hi> he, <hi>p.</hi> 5, 6, 7. would make the Reader believe, that I
bring them immediately to prove Infants diſcipled. And the like uſe he
maketh, <hi>p.</hi> 6, 7. of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures whereby I prove, <hi>p.</hi> 5.
that the Name <hi>[Holy]</hi> is given to the Church and its Members. So that,
either from great Ignorance or Inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, he may bluſh that he beats the
Air, and abuſeth me.</p>
            <p>As to my firſt Argument, <hi>That ſome Infants are diſcipled
ſo as to have the Name of Trinity upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt, he denieth my Antecedent; ſaying, That no Infants are
diſcipled at all, much leſs ſo as to have the Name of Father, Son and
Spirit upon them.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer, I evidenced it various ways: They are ſaid to be
<hi>[holy,]</hi> and ſo are diſcipled: <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103339:4"/> God hath put his
Name upon them before their Baptiſm, though it is ſolemnly ſignalized and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared after, when they are baptized.</p>
            <p>His firſt Reaſon, <hi>p. 3. from</hi> Act. 10. 28. <hi>is
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in my Book,</hi> p. 49, 50, 51. I grant there is no diſtinction
between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> but thoſe of both who are
viſibly in Covenant (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Adult, or Infants) are more clean than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
who are out of Covenant; and are a holy People, differenced from others, <hi>if
not by Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litative, yet by Relative Holineſs in Church-ſtate,</hi> Rom.
11. 16. 1 Pet. 2. 9. as of old, and nothing here againſt it.</p>
            <p>As to his ſecond Reaſon, I ſay, Men, by the Word of God, are
to be inſtrumental to bring Men within the Covenant, which extendeth to their
Seed; therefore alſo to make Infants Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. Some may be made
Diſciples without actual teaching, or learning; as we put Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to
School, who at firſt learn nothing. Learned <hi>Spanhemius</hi> well
obſerveth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>non ſignificat ſolum docere, ſed
Diſcipulos facere, &amp; aequipollet,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Joh. 4.
2. Dub. Evang. Par. 3. p.</hi> 93. giving Reaſons for it.</p>
            <p>I do not ſay, that all who are under Means for Inſtruction
(though Perſecutors) are Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but all who are in the School of
Chriſt's Church; of which, ſome are Infants. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed of Believing
<hi>Jews</hi> were in it (by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. and ſo, when that
was ſpoken, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19. (not being broken off till after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;)
and ſo alſo the Seed of Believing <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proved ſome Infants to be Diſciples, from <hi>Act.</hi> 15.
10. He denies that every one were Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <pb n="4" facs="tcp:103339:5"/> whom they
would have circumciſed, yet proves it not. But all which the Apoſtle
bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them for impoſing Circumciſion practical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon, are called by
him Diſciples, and theſe were principally Infants, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 10,
11, 12. Will he ſay, they were not blamed for laying Circumciſion upon
Infants? His Inſtance of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Sprinkling is not parallel, becauſe Infant
is not a <hi>Genus</hi> for all that we would have baptized.</p>
            <p>I proved, ſome Infants had the Name of the Trinity upon them, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. they are <hi>[holy.]</hi> This Holineſs he takes for
being Legitimate, but anſwers not what I ſaid againſt it; nor doth he
prove all to be holy that are legitimate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Elſe,] i. e.</hi> Say ſome, If one be not a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; or
<hi>[elſe,]</hi> if the Unbeliever were not ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to or by the
Believer, then the Children were unclean, not illegitimate: For where there is
no Sanctification of one, to or by the other, but both are Infidels or
Unbelievers, yet the Children are legitimate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 4. are no
Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards. The being <hi>[holy]</hi> then muſt be by a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration unto
God.</p>
            <p>There is no Good in Sin, but it becometh of humbling and abaſing
uſe to the Soul, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally is turned by God to Good to it; which
I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>C.</hi> intendeth, by its being ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to. And
this is no new Doctrine, but as old as the Days of <hi>Hezekiah, 2 Chron.</hi>
32. 25, 26. and <hi>Paul, 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
            <p>And <hi>if all Infants be in a viſible State of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by
the Covenant of Grace,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> ſaith they are, <hi>p.
19. then they have the Name of the Trinity upon them, for the Covenant is a
part of his Name,</hi> and ſo they are diſcipled; and what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103339:5"/> hinders their being baptized? Doth not <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.
19 command it?</p>
            <p>He thinks then they ought to partake of the Lord's Table. But are
they as capable of Self-Examination, and of that Eating and Drinking, and
Spiritual Growth, as they are of being waſhed?</p>
            <p>As to my ſecond Argument, <hi>from ſome Infants being
viſibly or externally in the Covenant made with</hi> Abraham:</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>He premiſeth, that the Covenant of Grace with</hi>
Abraham <hi>was Twenty four Years before Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion: Others under it,
as</hi> Salah,—<hi>not ſo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed: And others were, to whom the
Covenant of Grace ſeems to have the leaſt extent, as</hi> Iſhmael,
Eſau, <hi>Bond-men,</hi>—p. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then if by Covenant, Mr.</hi> P. <hi>means the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of
Circumciſion and Infants of Chriſtians, or the Covenant of Grace,</hi> Gen.
12. <hi>he denies the</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: <hi>But if Infants be in a viſible State
of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet he denieth the Conſequence of the</hi> Major, <hi>that
they are to be baptized,</hi> p. 10.</p>
            <p>Anſ 1. <hi>The Covenant of Grace was made and publiſhed
before</hi> Abraham, Gen. 3. 15. and thoſe might have Salvation by it through
Chriſt; as <hi>Salah, Arphaxad.</hi>—Then the Church was Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical,
but no ſuch clear Declaration of the Subjects, and their Church-ſtate and
Privilege, in a Community of many Families for publick Worſhip and
Ordinances; no ſuch Sign or To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Covenant for Infants, till
Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was granted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. And after that Grant to
<hi>Abraham,</hi> all good Men that could were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to joyn with him, or
his Seed, as the only Church in ſuch Order then in the World, as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103339:6"/> they would enjoy ſuch Church-Privileges: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his
Servants which were Profeſſors, <hi>v. 13. Gen.</hi> 18. 19. and the
Proſelytes, <hi>Exod. 12. 48, 49. Iſa.</hi> 56. 3, 6.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>I mean that Covenant which Circumciſion was a Token
of,</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>v.</hi> 7, to 15.</p>
            <p>Indeed, This is the ſame Covenant, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, with
that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. but in a new Edition; with a Declaration of the ancient
Subjects, and an Enlargement of Privileges, as aforeſaid, which expreſly
extended to the Infant-Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7, 9, 12 In the ſame Covenant
and Breath, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> himſelf, and alſo his Seed, are commanded to
be circumciſed; and that as a Token of the Covenant between God and him,
<hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, 11. He and his Seed then were in the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and
Circumciſion was of the ſame uſe to him and others: And that Covenant was
not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Circumciſion and the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but that (at
leaſt viſibly) God would be a God to them; and there is a double
Aſſurance thereof, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. and that clearly was a Covenant of
Grace, and is ſtill continuing; for it was to him a Seal of the
Righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
            <p>It is then his groſs Miſtake, to think that the Covenant,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 12. is one, and that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother diſtinctione.
Indeed, the Sign Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is ceaſed, but the Covenant is not
repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as to the Subject of it, Infants: This cannot be proved. 'Tis true,
ſome did forfeit their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, external Intereſt in the Covenant, as
<hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> and ſo may Profeſſors of the
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel alſo, after duly baptized: But they were ſo in Covenant before,
as it had been broken if the Token had been neglected, or not applied,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:103339:6"/> 3. <hi>At laſt, he denieth the Conſequence
of the</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor; which is to ſay, <hi>That though ſome Infants be
viſibly or externally in the Covenant which God made with</hi> Abraham,
<hi>yet by the Will of Chriſt they are not to be baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am glad to hear Men of this Perſuaſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Infants
within that Covenant; which indeed they muſt do, or elſe ſhew a Repeal of
that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as to the Subjects of it, which I think they can never prove.
But I am ſorry this Man granteth Infants being in that Covenant upon ſuch a
corrupt, unſcriptural Principle, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Infants are in a
viſible State of Salvation by the Covenant of Grace; he muſt ſay by the
Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> if he deny my <hi>Major,</hi> which is
grounded upon that; and it will be impoſſible for him to prove all Infants
in the World to be the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that in the very mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of it importing a Limitation.</p>
            <p>The ground of his Denial is, <hi>p.</hi> 10. upon a great
Miſtake, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Covenant of Grace muſt be abſtracted from
the Covenant of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; whereas that which Circumciſion is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
to (as I have proved) is the Covenant of Grace, only in a new Edition. Alſo
he ſaith, <hi>[That never required the Application of any Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to
Infants, as a Pledge of it, either before the Law, or as it is now
eſtabliſhed—in the Goſpel.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which is falſe; for Circumciſion was ſuch a Pledge and
Token of the Covenant, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to Infants, above Four hundred Years
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 17. and ſo Baptiſm under the Goſpel,
<hi>Act.</hi> 2. 38, 39. for that is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon that Ground and
Encouragement, that the Promiſe is to them; and that is there to a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103339:7"/> double Subject <hi>[You Repenters, and your Seed,]</hi> and
ſo to Infants, and ſo they are commanded to be baptized. All that are under
the Ground and Encouragement unto the Duty of being baptized, are obliged to
the Duty; and ſome Infants are under that, for the Promiſe is to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. ſpeaketh not expreſly of Baptiſm, but it
commandeth the Keeping the Covenant by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Token of it, which now is
not Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but Baptiſm; and ſo commandeth that even to Infants,
ſeeing they are in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as aforeſaid; and there is no
Scripture-Warrant to delay the applying that firſt Token of it after
Opportunity is offered. If it were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited (as Circumciſion was) to the
Eighth Day, it might be delayed till then, but now may be applied before. The
Females were uncapable, wanting the part, and yet were deemed circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in
the Males, for all <hi>Iſrael</hi> are called the Circumciſion: Which
anſwers his <hi>p.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>It ſtill runs there in his Head, that all I ſay is brought
forthwith to prove Infant-Baptiſm; whereas I prove other Mediums in order to
it. Thus, <hi>p.</hi> 8. I mention <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 16, 17. only to prove
Remiſſion of Sins to be a great Bleſſing of the Covenant: He,
<hi>p.</hi> 11. dreams that I muſt mean it of Infants.</p>
            <p>So I mention the Second Commandment, as requiring the obſerving
Goſpel-Inſtitutions, as Baptiſm after the alteration of the Sign, as of
old it required Circumciſion: He fancieth, that I produce it preſently to
prove Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>So I, <hi>p.</hi> 41. mention <hi>Matth. 16. 18. Rom. 16. 16, 1
Cor. 12. 27. &amp;c.</hi> to prove that the Church is Chriſt's: He,
<hi>p.</hi> 13. conceiteth, that I would <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103339:7"/> hereby prove
Infants viſibly Chriſt's; which I do by other <hi>Mediums.</hi> And here he
talketh that Infants may be ſaved who were never baptized, which was not
there my Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>I am weary of his Impertinencies, but hope that by ſerious
reading my Book, any judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſon will have enough there to anſwer
him.</p>
            <p>Abraham <hi>had an Eccleſiaſtical Seed, even of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi>
Gen. 17. The Infant-Seed of <hi>Jews</hi> were broken off with their Parents,
from external In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in, and Privilege by the Covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.
unleſs he can prove the Infants remained in Covenant ſtill.</p>
            <p>The Seed of Believers are viſibly under the Promiſe, the Word
of Faith, as the Seed of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are not, and ſo are of the Faith.] I ſee
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to invalidate what I ſaid thereof.</p>
            <p>I ſaid, <hi>Infants Intereſt in the Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17.
<hi>is not cut off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtead of proving a Repeal, and the Cutting them off, without
which, all that he or others ſay is nothing, he replieth,</p>
            <p>Obj. 1. <hi>Infants had as good Right to the Covenant of Grace
before Circumciſion, and have the ſame Right now,</hi> v. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>And what if they had, and have it? That is for me, not
against me.</hi> But, under favour, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was a new Privilege, which
Infants had not before, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>However, this doth not prove them cut off from any, but the
contrary.</p>
            <p>Obj. 2. <hi>No Perſon's Right to Circumciſion did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe out
of the Covenant of Grace, but it did only iſſue from the Command of
God,</hi> p. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103339:8"/> Anſ. 1. <hi>Here is no Syllable to prove
that Infant-Intereſt in the Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>is cut off:</hi> Some
Infants certainly had it, and ſo muſt ſtill, unleſs there be a
Repeal.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The Command is expreſs to all the Seed of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,
<hi>to keep the Covenant by applying the Token:</hi> And Infants are expreſly
concerned in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9, 10, 11, 12. and ſo all
Infants within that Covenant are under that Command ſtill, unleſs cut off.
'Tis true, the Sign of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is changed, but the Covenant is the
ſame, and the Subject of it the ſame: So that whether the Right ariſeth
from the Covenant, or from the Command, or both, it matters not; all his Seed,
Infants and all in it, by the Command, are to paſs under the Sign: And
Circumciſion then being a Token of the Covenant, the Right to it muſt
ariſe from the Covenant, although a Command was the Direction for applying
the Sign.</p>
            <p>Obj. 3. <hi>As Circumciſion did not give</hi> Abraham'<hi>s Seed
an Intereſt in the Covenant of Grace, ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogation did not take that
Interest from them: He inſtanceth in the delay of it to</hi> Moſes <hi>his
Child, the Omiſſion Forty Years in the Wilderneſs:—Infants now have
no part in the Covenant of Circumciſion, yet they loſt nothing by it. And
then he ſpeaketh of the Typical Covenant of Circumciſion being made
void,</hi> p. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Anſ. 1. <hi>Who ſaith that Circumciſion did give them
Interest in the Covenant of Grace?</hi> Rather a being in that Covenant gave
Intereſt in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, which was a Token of it. <hi>Moſes</hi> his
delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying of Circumciſion was his Sin, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 24, 25, 26. and
had like to have coſt him his Life; <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103339:8"/> and
<hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Omiſſion of it was their Sin. And is it no Loſs, in
Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi>'s Account, to be cut off from External Privileges,
unleſs Men be wholly cut off from the Covenant of Grace, and the Salvation
thereof? Is it nothing for God to ſay, <hi>Loami?</hi> The Taking away
Circumciſion was a Mercy, the Lord giving Baptiſm in lieu of it; but if he
had taken away that, and all Church-Privilege, and External Covenant-Intereſt
alſo, from Infants, which once they had, it muſt needs be a great Loſs,
an unſpeakable Diſadvantage, a ſore Judgment.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Now he declareth that Covenant which Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion did
belong to, void, and diſtinguiſhed from the Covenant of Grace, and calleth
it a Typical Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> But not one Syllable of Scripture-Evidence for any
ſuch thing: We muſt believe it, if he will, becauſe <hi>ipſe
dixit.</hi> Here he ſhould have proved a Repeal of that Covenant with
<hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> and not having done this, he hath done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. I believe
that the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. wherein twice God declareth himſelf a
God to the Seed of <hi>Abraham, v.</hi> 7, 8. the Sign whereof, Circumciſion,
<hi>Abraham</hi> received, as a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. muſt needs be a Covenant of Grace, no Typical Covenant,
nor void; for that Righteouſneſs was not of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant only for
<hi>Canaan,</hi> but of Grace, for Eternal Life. And that <hi>Abraham</hi>
received it as a Sign of one Covenant, and his Seed of another, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be
proved: The contrary is plain, <hi>viz.</hi> that both had it by the ſame
Command and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>But now Mr. <hi>Grantham, p. 19, 20, &amp;c.</hi> findeth a
<hi>Medium</hi> by a new Poſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103339:9"/> Poſit. <hi>That all Infants (as ſuch) are
in a Viſible State of Salvation by the Covenant of Grace, and ſo are of the
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church of God, and cannot be put out of that bleſſed State,
till by their voluntary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from God, by chuſing ſinful Ways, they
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>If this were true, one would think that all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,
without exception, might be baptized, being ſo in the Covenant of Grace, and
of the Church; for then they are made Diſciples, and ſo are expreſly
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be baptized,</hi> Matth. 28. 19.</p>
            <p>I hope Mr. <hi>Barret</hi> or ſome other will examine this
Poſition, I ſhall not now inſiſt long upon it. If never ſo many
Infants be in a State of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or be ſaved, this is not againſt my
Principle of Infant Baptiſm: I would not diminiſh the number of ſaved
Ones; however, I think this to be a falſe, unſcriptural Poſition.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>He telleth us of five Demonſtrations,</hi> p. 20,
<hi>to 24. but all of them come to one poor Argument from the Covenant of
Grace,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. <hi>which he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth was made with all Mankind, with
the whole World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. 1. <hi>That all Mankind, or the whole World, is this Seed
of the Woman with whom the Covenant of Grace was made, is altogether without
Proof;</hi> and ſo all his Demonſtrations are wholly groundleſs. Let him
but form an Argument from <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. that is univerſal, and any may
ſee it will have a <hi>Non ſequitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The utmoſt here ſaid is, that a Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or ſome
of her Seed, ſhould be ſaved; but it is not ſaid, All the Woman's Seed,
as ſuch, ſhould be ſaved. His Poſition ſhould be his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of
all his Demonſtrations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>viz. That all Infants (as ſuch) are in a
viſible State of Salvation <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103339:9"/> by the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
But ſuch a Concluſion hath no Footing in, no Countenance from this Text,
not ſo much as by Conſequence. I think I have better than this for
Infant-Baptiſm; and I might ſay as well, that all their Seed have the
Spirit poured out upon them, and the Word in their Mouth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.
3. and 59. 21.</p>
            <p>The truth is, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. cometh in as a Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of
Puniſhment or Severity againſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, (as any obſerving Eye may
ſee,) yet imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Promiſe of Mercy, attainable by ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Men, through Chriſt, a Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Until <hi>Adam</hi> did take hold
of that Promiſe by Faith in that Seed, Chriſt, he remained out of Covenant,
as others, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8, 12. When <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was actually and
perſonally admitted into the Covenant of Grace, yet it was not as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
publick Perſon, and Head of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, repreſenting all his Seed, as
he was before his Fall a Head of the Covenant of Nature; for then
<hi>Adam</hi>'s After-Sins againſt the Covenant would have been imputed to
all his Seed, as his former were, againſt the Covenant of Works, <hi>Rom. 5.
12, &amp;c. v.</hi> 20.—</p>
            <p>Now every individual Man was perſonally to be in Covenant; and
if he derived external Privilege, it was only to his next or immediate
Seed.</p>
            <p>Hence, if <hi>Adam</hi>'s Infant-Seed might have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Privilege by being his Poſterity, (or any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Abraham,)</hi> yet if
any of them after rejected the Covenant, (as <hi>Cain</hi> did,) they caſt
themſelves out of that external Privilege, and their Infant-Seed with them.
So in after Generations, <hi>Hagar,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> her Seed were
caſt out, and <hi>Eſau</hi> and <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103339:10"/> his, the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> and theirs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. and thoſe were Strangers
to the Covenants, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 12. See alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.
28.</p>
            <p>I know not that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> (two Perſons)
made a Church: Let Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> prove it. But that Promiſe laid a
Foundation for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting a Viſible Church afterward.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Adam</hi>'s Family was the Church, (as you ſay,) and the
whole World, or all Mankind that then was (and ſo his Infant-Seed) were
Members of it, yet <hi>Cain</hi> and his Seed were ſoon rejected;
notwithſtanding which, many Perſons believing in that Seed, Chriſt, were
ſo ſaved in after Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, through that Promiſe. But that all
Infants of rejected <hi>Cain, Iſhmael,</hi> or <hi>Eſau</hi> were in a
viſible State of Salvation, and of the Viſible Church, or that all dying in
Infancy are certainly ſaved, appeareth not, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. Mr.
<hi>Grantham</hi> aſſerting, it is Preſumption without Proof.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>That</hi> Gen. 3. 15. <hi>mentioneth a Seed of the Serpent,
which is part of the World,</hi> as well as the Seed of the Woman, which the
Covenant of Grace extendeth to; and hence this Text which he alledgeth is
excluſive of ſome, and ſo confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his Demonſtration. For if there be
in it another oppoſite Seed, then all Mankind, or the whole World, cannot be
compriſed in the Seed of the Woman, who are under this Promiſe. Will he
ſay, the Seed of the Serpent are viſibly in a State of Salvation, by the
Covenant of Grace: Or that they are no part of the World?</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Only thoſe are this Seed of the Woman, under this
Covenant or Promiſe, who have Enmity againſt the Serpent, and ſuch Power
over him, as to bruiſe his Head: And this is excluſive of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:103339:10"/> For that is expreſly the Qualification of
the Seed of the Woman here intended: Yea, the whole of the Promiſe which here
extendeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of Mankind is, <hi>Gen. 3. 15. I will put Enmity between
thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy
Head;</hi> the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Words concern the Serpent, <hi>viz. his bruiſing
his Heel.</hi> So then, none elſe are this Seed of the Woman, or viſibly in
a State of Salvation, by this Covenant, but ſuch in whom is found that Enmity
againſt the Serpent, ſo as to conflict with, and prevail againſt him.
Therefore this <hi>[Seed of the Woman]</hi> can be only Chriſt, 1
<hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14, 15. and ſuch as believe in him; for,
1 <hi>Joh. 5. 4. This is the Victory,—even our Faith.</hi> Hence the
whole World cannot be here intended.</p>
            <p>If whole Mankind, yea, all Infants were that Seed of the Woman,
then all Infants have En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the Serpent, and then they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of, yea have Love to God, and Faith in him, and ſo may be baptized.</p>
            <p>It is the Covenant which I called the great Charter of Heaven,
<hi>viz.</hi> of the God of Heaven: And as others, by denying Infants
Intereſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, do take from it, ſo let him take heed of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to
it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103339:11"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THE foregoing Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi> ſhould have
been publiſhed ſoon after its Date, 1687. with Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s, if
his had not been out before he expected; and it is at the deſire of ſome
Friends, that now it cometh forth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He intimateth,</hi> p. 9. <hi>that</hi> Salah, Heber, &amp;c.
<hi>lived after</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>and were not circumciſed, nor had
Obligation to Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>this is more than he knows,</hi> ſeeing ſo little is
revealed to us of the way of their Worſhip in that Day. And it ſeemeth to
be falſe, becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> then was declared <hi>the Father of many
Nations,</hi> v. 5. And ſo Believers of other Nations were then his Seed, and
obliged, if ſome lawful Impediment hindred not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>However, this is certain, that believing Gentiles in
Goſpel-Times are graffed into, or intereſted in the ſame Covenant that
was made with</hi> Abraham, Gen. 17. <hi>and his Seed;</hi> the ſame Olive
which the <hi>Jews</hi> were broken off from, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 11, to 27. And
as of old they were circumciſed, not merely by virtue of a Command, but as a
Token of the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 14. hence all under that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
that could, were to ſubmit to it, and that as a Mark of Diſtinction; for
they were diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from others by Circumciſion: Even ſo it is now
as to Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103339:11"/> And whereas Mr. <hi>Grantham denieth that the
Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>is a Goſpel-Covenant, or a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of
Grace,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>is his groſs Errour; for the Apoſtle proveth
Juſtification in Goſpel-Times to be by Grace from this Covenant with</hi>
Abraham, Rom. 4. 1, 2, 3, 4, 16, 17.</p>
            <p>This is the very Ground which his Argument is built upon, <hi>viz.
That we under the Goſpel are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the ſame way that</hi> Abraham
<hi>was, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by Grace:</hi> By the Promiſe, and not by the Law. If
this could be denied, all his Arguing were vain and falſe.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>that Covenant with</hi> Abraham, Gen. 17. <hi>which
Circumciſion did belong to, is that which his Argument is bottomed upon,</hi>
as is evident, <hi>Rom. 4. 16. Therefore it is of Faith, that it might be by
Grace.</hi>—How doth he prove that? <hi>V. 17. As it is written, I have
made thee a Father of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>—Now it is very obſervable,
that this is quoted cut of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 4, 5. and it is no where elſe in
foregoing Editions of the Covenant: <hi>It is not found in</hi> Gen. 12.
<hi>nor in</hi> Gen. 15. <hi>therefore that,</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>was a
Goſpel-Covenant, and not ceaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> think that the Apoſtle would ſeek
to prove our Juſtification by an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated Covenant, and a legal one too, as
he would have this be?</p>
            <p>I might prove it a <hi>Goſpel-Covenant from his calling
Circumciſion a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> Rom. 4. 11. and
there is no Syllable in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, declaring it to be of one Uſe to
<hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and of another to other Perſons.</p>
            <p>Alſo, <hi>From his ſetting this Promiſe to</hi> Abraham,
<hi>in oppoſition to the Law,</hi> Rom. 4. 13, 14. it is
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinguiſhed from that, as elſewhere, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 17.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103339:12"/> This evidenceth it to be a Covenant of Grace, and ſtill
in force; and if for Juſtification, then alſo for External Privileges to
the Subjects of it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>once more from</hi> Gen. 17. 7, 8. <hi>where twice he
promiſeth to be</hi> [their God] <hi>which is the great Bleſſing of the
new Covenant,</hi> Heb 8. 10.</p>
            <p>What is objected <hi>to make it a legal Covenant, as that
Circumciſion made Men Debtors to the whole Law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is
vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For either it ſpeaketh of it in the Senſe of the Falſe
Prophets, who urge Circumciſion—for Juſtification and Salvation:</hi>
And thus if Men ſhould urge any Duty, even Baptiſm, upon ſuch a legal
Ground, it would make them Debtors to the whole Law. <hi>Or it imports, that
neither Circumciſion, nor any Works of the Law, do profit, unleſs all be
performed;</hi> for the Law promiſed nothing but upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Obedience,
<hi>Gal. 3. 10. Rom.</hi> 10. 5.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. It maketh no mention of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, much
leſs of all of them. What Share they have in a Promiſe, muſt be deduced
from other Texts, not from this. Will he ſay, that <hi>[Seed]</hi> and
<hi>[Infants,]</hi> or <hi>[all Infants,]</hi> are ſynonymous? Here no more
is ſaid of all Infants being the Seed of the Woman, than of ſome of them
being the Seed of the Serpent.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add, that if Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> ſhould reply
ſo as I be convinced that the ſubſtance of what I have here written be
not Truth, then I intend a Retractation: But if I be ſilent, it may be
concluded that I do not account him worth the Anſwering.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103339:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books, Printed for, and are to be Sold
by</hi> Edward Giles, <hi>Bookseller in</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, <hi>near the</hi>
Market-Place.</head>
            <p>SEveral Diſcourſes concerning Actual Providence.</p>
            <p>A Word in Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Defenſive Armour againſt four of <hi>Satan</hi>'s moſt fiery
Darts.</p>
            <p>Sermons upon the whole 1ſt and 2d Chapter of
<hi>Canticles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirteen Sermons upon ſeveral uſeful Subjects. All
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>John Collings.</hi> D. D. of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way of the Spirit in bringing Souls to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Glory of Chriſt ſet forth, with the Neceſſity of
Faith: In ſeveral Sermons. Both by Mr. <hi>Thomas Allen,</hi> late Paſtor
of a Church at <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Walk with God and Chriſt, a Chriſtian's Gain.
By Mr. <hi>Timothy Armitage,</hi> late Miniſter at <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Preciouſneſs of Chriſt, and of the
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of Faith.</p>
            <p>Precious Promiſes the Portion of Overcomers.</p>
            <p>Sermons on five ſeveral uſeful Subjects. All by Mr. <hi>John
Longher,</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saint's <hi>Ebenezer.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Francis Engliſh,</hi>
late Miniſter in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Directions to ſpell <hi>Engliſh</hi> right.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the <hi>Proteſtant Reformation,</hi> as it was
begun by <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The dead Saints ſpeaking: Being a Sermon preached upon the Death
of Mr. <hi>Newcomb,</hi> of <hi>Deadham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miracles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ordinary Matter of Prayer, drawn into Queſtions and
Anſwers.</p>
            <p>Two Treatiſes: The firſt, Of Rejoycing in the Lord Jeſus in
all Caſes and Conditions. The ſecond, Of a Chriſtian's Hope in Heaven,
and Freedom from Condemnation by Chriſt. Both by Mr. <hi>Robert Aſty</hi>
late Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obedience to Magiſtrates: Recommended in a Sermon preached
<hi>September</hi> the 9th, 1683. being the Thankſgiving-Day for His
Majeſty's Deliverance. By <hi>Jonathan Clapham,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of
<hi>Wramplingham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:103339:13"/> A Preſent for Youth, and an Example for the Aged:
Two Diſcourſes; one, Of Spiritual Bleſſings; the other, That God hath
an high Account of the leaſt Grace in the Saints. By Mr. <hi>John
Cromwell,</hi> late Paſtor of a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Infant-Baptiſm of Chriſt's Appointment. By Mr. <hi>Samuel
Petto,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Sudbury</hi> in
<hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the Converſion of Sinners to God, in Chriſt; the
Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, Nature, Means and Signs of it: With a Concluding Speech to the
Unconverted.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Thomas Grantham</hi>'s Book, called A
Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue between the Baptiſt and Presbyterian. Both by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin
Finch,</hi> Paſtor of a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sincerity: <hi>Or,</hi> The Upright Man's Walk to Heaven:
Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in ſeveral Sermons in the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Michael,</hi>
in <hi>Long-ſtratten,</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi> By <hi>James Oldfield,</hi>
late Miniſter there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexipharmacon Spirituale:</hi> Being a Defenſative
againſt the Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Sting of Death: <hi>Or,</hi> The Great Expedient
how to make the Bed of the Grave ſo eaſie, that we may lie down in Peace,
and take our Reſt. By <hi>Samuel Snowden,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at
<hi>Newton</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt ſet forth: In ſeveral Sermons upon the 17th Chapter
to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Robert Ottee,</hi> late Paſtor to a
Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in <hi>Beckles</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sacramental Diſcourſes on ſeveral ſelect Subjects. To
which is added, A Diſcourſe of the Life of Faith. By <hi>Chriſtopher
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marett,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcovery of Audacious Inſolence againſt the Doctrine of
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> vented in a malicious Pamphlet, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
againſt the Presbyterians, by <hi>Thomas Grantham:</hi> Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Poem
thereon. And a Poſtſcript, wherein ſome of the Citizens of
<hi>Norwich</hi> are more particularly concerned and cautioned.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103339:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
